<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe description of Ireland: made in this yeare, 1589. by Robert Payne, vnto xxv. of his partners for whome he is vndertaker there. Truely published verbatim, according to his letters, by Nich. Gorsan one of the sayd partners, for that he would his countreymen should be partakers of the many good notes therein contayned</title>
            <author>Payne, Robert, fl. 1589.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09178</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19490</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102904</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838665</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838665</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3052</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09178)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3052)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1149:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe description of Ireland: made in this yeare, 1589. by Robert Payne, vnto xxv. of his partners for whome he is vndertaker there. Truely published verbatim, according to his letters, by Nich. Gorsan one of the sayd partners, for that he would his countreymen should be partakers of the many good notes therein contayned</title>
                  <author>Payne, Robert, fl. 1589.</author>
                  <author>Gorsan, Nicholas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Dawson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  Description and travel --  To 1700.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3052:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3052:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Briefe deſcription of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: Made in this yeare,</hi> 1589.</p>
            <p>by Robert Payne, vnto xxv. of his <hi>partners for whome he is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaker</hi> there.</p>
            <p>Truely publiſhed verbatim, <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his letters, by Nich. Gorſan one</hi> of the ſayd partners, for that he would his countreymen ſhould be partakers of the many good Notes therin contayned.
AT LONDON, Printed by Thomas Dawſon.</p>
            <p>1589.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:3052:2"/>
            <head>To his very good friend M. <hi>Nicholas Gorſan of Trowell in the Countie</hi> of Nottingham, and the reſt of his xxv. partners for Ireland, giue theſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ET not the reportes of thoſe that haue ſpent all their owne and what they could y any meanes get from others in England, diſcourage you from Ireland, although they and ſuch others by bad dealinges haue wrought a generall diſcredite to all Engliſh men, in that countrie which are to the Iriſhe vnknowne.</p>
            <p>Theſe men will ſay there is great danger in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelling the countrie, and much more to dwell or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habite there: yet are they freed from three of the greateſt dangers: firſt, they cannot meete in al that land any worſſe then themſelues: ſecondly, they need not feare robbing for that they haue not any thing to looſe: laſtly, they are not like to run in debt, for that there is none wil truſt them. The greateſt matter which troubleth them is, they cannot get any thing there but by honeſt trauell, which they are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorant of. Theſe men cannot tel what good
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3052:2"/>
fruites England hath, the which Ireland wanteth, neyther can they iuſtly ſay, but that it lyeth better for the vent of all commodities then England doth.</p>
            <p>What theſe men haue reported or what the ſimple haue credited, that woulde rather beleeue a runnea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate then trauell to ſee: I care not. But what I haue diſcouered or learned in that countrey, I will herein recite vnto you.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the people are of three ſortes, the better ſort are very ciuill and honeſtly giuen: the moſt of them greatly inclined to huſbandrie, although as yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkilfull, notwithſtanding, through their great trauel many of them are rich in cattel, ſome one man there milketh one hundred kine, and two or three hundred yeawes and goates, and reareth yearely moſt of their breed.</p>
            <p>Their entertainement for your dyet ſhalbe more welcome and plentifull, then cleanly and handſome, for although they did neuer ſee you before, they will make you the beſt cheare their countrey yeeldeth for two or three daies, &amp; take not any thing therefore. Moſte of them ſpeake good Engliſh and bring vp their children to learning. I ſawe in a Grammer ſchoole in <hi>Limberick,</hi> one hundred, and threeſcore ſchollers, moſt of them ſpeaking good and perfite Engliſh, for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they haue vſed to conſter the Latine into Engliſh. They keepe their promiſe faythfully, and are more deſirous of peace then our Engliſh men, for that in time of warres they are more char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3052:3"/>
And alſo they are fatter praies for the enemie who reſpecteth no perſon. They are quicke witted and of good conſtitution of bodie, they reforme them ſelues dayly more and more after the Engliſh man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: nothing is more pleaſing vnto them then to heare of good Iuſtices placed amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They haue a common ſaying which I am perſwaded they ſpeake vnfaynedly, which is, <hi>Defend me, &amp; ſpend me:</hi> meaning from the oppreſſion of the worſer ſort of our countreymen: They are obedient to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes, ſo that you may trauell through all the land without any danger or iniurie offered of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very worſt Iriſh, and be greatly releeued of the beſt.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort being leaſt in number are called <hi>Kernes,</hi> they are warlike men: moſt of that ſorte were ſlayne in the late warres.</p>
            <p>The third ſort, are a very idle people, not vnlike our Engliſh beggers, yet for the moſte part, of pure complexion and good conſtitution of body: one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt ouerſights in the better ſort is, for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they make not that idle ſort giue accompt of their life.</p>
            <p>They haue the Engliſhe lawes and gouernours as is in England: Firſt, there is a Lord deputy ouer the whole land, that repreſenteth her Maieſtie, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a Lord Chancellor, a Lord Treaſurer, a Lord chiefe Iuſtice, and all other Magiſtrates, Officers and Courtes, in like maner as belongeth to Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter.</p>
            <p>The land is deuided into fiue great parts: that is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3052:3"/>
to ſaye. <hi>Munſter, Lanſter, Conath, Meath,</hi> and <hi>Vlſter.</hi> In <hi>Munſter,</hi> are theſe vit. great countries: <hi>Owrm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Deaſmond, Corke, Waterford Typerare, Lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bericke,</hi> and <hi>Carrey:</hi> a great part of <hi>Munſter,</hi> was forfited to her Maieſtie by meanes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Deaſmondes</hi> late rebellion.</p>
            <p>There is two very riche countries called <hi>Kennory</hi> and <hi>Conelogh,</hi> both within the countie of <hi>Lemereck:</hi> they are called the gardens of the land for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> varietie and great plentie of all graine and fruites, and alſo there is more plentie of veniſon, fiſh and fowle then elſ where in Ireland, although in euery place there is great ſtore. This land belonged ſometime to the knight of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> valley, who for high treaſon was execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Lemerecke.</hi> Ouer euery part is an Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man liefetenant which hath authoritie as fully as the Marſhall, to erecute Marſhall lawes vpon the Iriſhe offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders at al times. Alſo there are Iudges of aſſize for euery circuit, who keepe their aſſiſes as our Iudges doe: if any matter be to be tryed there betweene an Engliſh man and an Iriſh, the Iury is half Engliſh and halfe Iriſh. There is a ſheriffe of euery countie, with vnderſheriffes, Arrant Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffes, &amp; al other officers appertaining. Alſo there is a conuenient number of Iuſtices of peace in euery countie with Conſtables and pettie Conſtables, who keepe their quarter ſeſſions orderly.</p>
            <p>The countrey is ſcituated ſome what neerer the Equinoctiall lyne then England, but yet for that it
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3052:4"/>
lyeth more vpon the Ocean ſeas &amp; is full of Riuers &amp; ſmal brookes, it is not ſo hote in ſummer as Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land, neyther is it ſo cold in winter, for that the ſeas fretteth away the Ice &amp; Snowe there, much more then in England.</p>
            <p>The general Map of Ireland, which is ioyned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the olde Map of England, is moſte falſe: The au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour (as it ſeemeth) drew them both by report, and the common computation of myles: and made his Scale after the Engliſh meaſure, that is one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand paces, or fiue thouſand footes to the myle: but therein he greatly deceiued himſelfe, for the ſhorteſt myles in England are much longer then that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and an Iriſh myle is longer then two of thoſe myles, by which meanes he hath made the Map of England leſſe by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> halfe then it ſhould be. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, he hath ouer reached in his nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of pariſh Churches, and the Map of Ireland littell more then one fourth of that it would be, if it were truely drawen. This ſeemeth ſtrange, and hath deceiued many ignorant in Geometrie: but alwayes take this for a principle, that the ſquare of two myles con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayneth iuſt foure tymes ſo much as the ſquare of one myle, and ſo of al proportions from the greateſt to the leaſt: wherefore as much may be ſayd of the long myle which containeth two ſhort myles.</p>
            <p>Some miſtruſt that the Spaniardes will enter the land, &amp; that the Iriſh wil releeue them: no doubt there are ſome Traytors in Ireland, I would I
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3052:4"/>
could truely ſay there were none in England: but this I dare aſſure you the greater number, and al the better ſort doe deadly hate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Spaniardes, &amp; yet I thinke they beare them fayre weather, for that they are the popes champions, &amp; a great part of the Iriſh (for want of good preaching &amp; diſcipline) are greatly inclined to papiſtrie.</p>
            <p>But their intertaineme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t this laſt yeare amongſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iriſh (notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding they brought the popes holy candles &amp; pardons) ſheweth how they affect Spa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iſh gouerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Moſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better ſort of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iriſh haue read of their mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſterous cruelties in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weſt India<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, where they moſt tiranouſly haue murthered many millions moe of thoſe ſimple creatures the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now liu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in Ireland, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch as ſought their fauours by offering vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had, neuer reſiſting nor of fering the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any harme. Wherfore I doubt not that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iriſh are ſo fooliſh to entertain ſuch proud gueſtes knowing their tyrannie, &amp; hauing not ſo well deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at their hands as thoſe ſimple ſoules who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſo cruelly murdered. Neyther are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Spaniardes ſo vn wiſe to truſt thoſe iriſh, who ſo lately imbrued their hands in their bloud, ſlaying them as doggs in ſuch plentifull maner, that their garments went about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countrey to be ſold, as good cheape as beaſtes ſkins. If you haue not the ſayd booke of the Spaniſhe cruelties, I pray you buy it, it is wel worth the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, I haue for got the title, but it is of a ſmall vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume in quarto: it is written by a learned Biſhop of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3052:5"/>
their owne countrey about forty yeares ſithens in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Caſtalian toonge,</hi> and dedicated to their king for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of thoſe cruelties: afterwardes tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Engliſh &amp; diuers other languages, to make their monſterous tyrannie knowne to the worlde. When you haue read the ſame, conunend it to our Catholickes that wil be ſaued by their workes, and yet will not giue God thankes at their meate, for that they will not once haue in their mouth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> praier for our Queene, annexed to our vſual thanks giuing at meate. I pray God open y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eies of their vpholders, and let them ſee what theſe men gape for, which is no doubt the ruine and ouerthrow of her highneſſe, whome I pray God preſerue. But none are ſo blind as they that will not ſe. The Catholikes are borne with for their conſcience ſake, yet from ſuch conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences ſpring all the Traiterous practiſes agaynſt her Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>Although ſome of ſmal iudgements (which thinke euery ſoile good that beareth long graſſe) haue fayled of their erpected woad crops, by meanes of their vn ſkilfull choyſe of ground, yet aſſuredly the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of the countrie are many moe then eyther the people can well vſe or I recite. Their ſoyle for the moſt part is very fertile, and apt for Wheate, Rye, Barly, Peaſon, Beanes, Oates, Woade, Mather, Rape, Hoppes, Hempe, Flaxe and al other graines and fruites y England any wiſe doth yeeld. There is much good timber in many places &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3052:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and ſo good to reaue, that a ſimple workeman with a Brak axe wil cleaue a great Oke, to boards of leſſe then one ynche thicke, xiiii. ynches broad and xv. footes in length, ſuch a board there is vſuallyſold for ii. d. ob. There is very riche and great plentie of Iron ſtone, and one ſort more then we haue in Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land, which they call Bogge myne, of the which a Smith there wil make at his forge Iron preſently. Alſo there is great ſtore of Lead Ore, &amp; Wood ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to mayntayne diuers Iron and lead workes (with good huſbandrie) for euer. A barrel of Wheat or a barrell of bay Salt contayning three buſhels &amp; a halfe of Wincheſter meaſure, is ſold there for iiii. s. Malt, Peaſon, Beanes, for ii. s. viii. d. Barly for ii. s. iiii. d. Oates for xx. d. a freth Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worth in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don x. s. for vi. d. xxiiii. Herrings or vi. Makerels, vi. ſea breames, a fat hen .xxx. Egges, a fat Pigge, one pound of Butter, or ii. gallo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of new Milke for ape<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. A redde Deare without the ſkinne, for ii. s. vi. d. A fat Beefe for xiii. s. iiii d. A fat Matto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for xviii. d.</p>
            <p>There be great ſtore of wild Swannes, Cranes, Pheſantes, Partriges, Heathcocks, Plouers green &amp; gray, Curlewes Woodcockes, Rayles, Quailes, &amp; al other fowles much more plentiful then in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and. You may buy a doſen of Quayles for iii. d. a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen of Woodcocks for iiii. d. &amp; all other fowls rata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie. Oyſters, muſkels, cockles and Samphiere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea coaſtes are to be had for gathering great plentie: the Phiſitions there hold, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Samphier is a
<pb n="01" facs="tcp:3052:6"/>
preſent remedie agaynſt the ſtone: you may buy the beſt Heafers there with Calues at their feet. for xx. s. a peece, the which are nothing inferiour to the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſorte of Lyncolnſhire breed. Their chiefe horſſes are of as great price as in England, but carthorſſes mares, and little hackneyes are of very ſmall price, the mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eſt Iriſh man diſdayneth to ryde on a mare. You may keepe a better houſe in Ireland for L. li. a yeare, then in England for CC. li a yeare. Al your commodities you may tranſport from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea ſide in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countie of Corke (where I haue prouided for eache of vs foure hundred Acres of land) to England for viii. d. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hundred waight, ſo that you make the ſame ready about S. Andrewes tide, when the herring fiſhers goe home from Irela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. The charg of which carriage for ſo much as you barrell, you may ſaue a great part through Cheapenes of the caſke, &amp; then wil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt of your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities, viz. Butter, Cheeſe. Bacon, Beefe, Honny, Ware, Tallowe, Corne, and Herring with diuers other Marchandize bee readie for the market.</p>
            <p>The worſſer ſorte of vndertakers which haue ſeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nories of her Maieſtie, haue done much hurt in the countrie, and diſcouraged many from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> voyage: for they haue entyced many honeſt men ouer. promiſing them much and performing nothing, no not ſo much as to paie their ſeruantes, &amp; workmen wages. They wil not let any terme, aboue xxi. yeres or three liues, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> demaund for rent xii. d. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Acre: this is ſo farre
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3052:6"/>
from the meaning of her Maieſtie, as appeareth by her highnes grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> as I think they haue, or ſhortly will make all their eſtates voyde. They finde ſuch profite from the Iriſhe tenantes, who giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fourth ſheafe of al their corne, and xvi. d. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earel<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for a beaſtes graſſe, beſides diuers other Iriſh accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med duties. So that they care not although they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer place any Engliſh man there. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better ſort of vnder takers being many good knights &amp; gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of great worſhip, do ſeek by al meanes poſſible to plant their landes with Engliſhmen according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meaning of her Maieſties graunt: they offer to any man either three hundreth acres of land in fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farme or foure hundred acres by leaſe for one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares, for vi. d. the acre without any fine.</p>
            <p>Sir Richard Greenefield taketh a verie good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for artificers &amp; labourers: he wil let any poore man of honeſt behauiour a houſe, xl. acres of land &amp; vi. milche Kyne for xl. s. the yeare, for the terme of three liues, and if any of theſe men after they haue bread on the ſame ſtocke a ſufficient number of cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell to ſtore their ground, doe deliuer their ſtocke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, then ſhal they pay but xx. s. rent for the reſt of their termes. And if any of the ſaid Kine be ſtolne, and the owner doe track which way they were dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from has ground, the ſayd ſir Richard will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer him ſo many Kyne for them, for that the law is there, if you tracke any ſtolne goodes into any mans land, hee muſt tracke them from him, or aunſwere
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3052:7"/>
them within xl. daies, ſo where the track ceaſeth, the goodes muſt be anſwered.</p>
            <p>A man may be aſwell and cleanely tabled at an Engliſh houſe in Ireland for the profit of fiue Kyne and fiftie ſheepe, all which will be bought for vii. li. x. s. &amp; for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rent of ſo much land as wil keep them, which is xx. s. the yeare, as at the beſt ordinarie in England for vi. d. a meale: all which amounteth but to xxxv. s. vi. d. a yeare, accounting ii. s. in the pound for intereſt of the ſtocke. Wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>en may be borded for the preſt<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of foure Kyne, xl. ſheepe, and xvi. s. rent. Seruants for iii. Kyne. xxx. ſheepe, and xii. s. rent. Children, for ii. kine, xx. ſheepe and viii. s. rent. Thus may a man that is xii. in houſhold, viz. Himſelfe, his wife, ii. ſeruauntes, and viii. children be very wel tab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a yeare for the profite of xxxi. Kyne, iii. C. and x. ſheep, &amp; vi. li. x. s. rent: al which ſtocke wil be bought for leſſe then lx. li. The vſe wherof being vi. li. the whole charge of a yeare for xii. perſons is xii. li. x. s. which is xx. s. x. d. a peece. This hath not bene long vſed there, but nowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Engliſhman thinketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe happie that can make ſuch a bargayne with an honeſt man: for although y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is not euery way to the geſſe aboue xii. li. x. s. may make the hoſt with good huſbandrie more then a hundred markes.</p>
            <p>One hundred pounds wil buy lx. milch kine, CCC. yeawes, xx. ſwyne, and a good teame: the ground to keep theſe cattell, &amp; vſe this tea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e on, wil be CCCC. acres at x. pound rent ſo your yearely charg will be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3052:7"/>
with intereſt of your mony, xx. li. for the which you may haue yeerely vpon good ſecurity with warrant of your ſtocke, xl. ſirkins of butter, and fortie great ways of cheeſe, of the milke gathered betwirt May, and Michaelmas, which at x. s. the firkin, and xxv. s. the waie, is threeſcore &amp; ten pounds, and the wooll and lamb of your ſheepe. cannot be ſo litle worth as xxx. li. a yeare, all which amounteth to one hundred poundes: ſo may you declare beſides your intereſt and rent, eightie pounds a yeere.</p>
            <p>To huſband this farme, your tenant muſt keepe viii. perſons, which may be well done with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of the ſwyne, wynter milke, calues and the crop which he ſhould get vpon your land w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your teame.</p>
            <p>Moſt of the coyne in Ireland, and that which the people generally deſire there, is baſe mony made of copper or braſſe, they will not change you an angell into that money without iiii. d. gaines: I would to God her Maieſtie would coyne foure hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand markes of the ſame, and lend it to the Engliſh marchantes gratis for two yeares, to be imployed there in mather, woade, rape, hoppes, hempe, flare and ſuch other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities, as might ſet ſome great number of our Engliſh men to work by which mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes (in my iudgement) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land might be very wel peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pled her Maieſtie diſburthened of a great part of her charge there, the marchantes made great gayners, and yet at the two yeares end paie her Maieſtie her full ſumme in currant Engliſh money for that baſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3052:8"/>
mettell, whereby her Maieſtie might gayne at leaſt CC. thouſand poundes without hurt to any, &amp; good to many thouſandes. I haue ſent you heerein cloſed an inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how you ſhal make a warraine for con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies of two acres of ground, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhalbe ſufficient for a gentlemans houſe in which warraine, you may alſo make an Orchard, and the connies ſhall not barke your trees nor make their berries vnder the rootes, neither ſhal the ſayd connies go foorth of two acres. Thus with my heartie commendations, I bid you heartily farewell. From my houſe at Paynes end, this xxv. of Iune. 1589.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing friend
Robert Payne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <head>The copie of an inſtruction for a <hi>Warraine.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FIrſt, you muſt chooſe two acres of very drie ground, and compaſſe it with a ditch as round as a circle, fiue footes deepe and ſeuen footes wide, let the ſlope ſide of your ditch be towardes your warraine, and that wayes throw vp all your earth, let the outſid be plum vpright, which you muſt preſently payle otherwiſe the earth wil ſal in: then plant your trees not aboue viii. ynches deep, and at the leaſt xxiiii foote aſunder, lay at euery roote cloſe about the tree, aſmuch peaſe ſtrawe as a man will carry vnder his arme, the which will keepe the roote moyſt in ſommer, &amp; warme from froſtes in winter. The beſt time to ſet your teees is ſhortly after Michaelmas: which verefieth an old prouerbe in Kent if thou wilt a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3052:8"/>
good tree haue, let him carry a greene leaſe to his graue. In the very middeſt of your grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d you muſt make a little lodge, in the which you muſt haue eight ſeueral hutches, ſo placed that they may be alwayes open into the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine, in euery hutche you muſt tye with a little chayne a tame bucke conny of the beſt kynde: then ſtore your warraine with 64. of the better ſort of tame female con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, which is for euery bucke viii. does, euery weeke the firſt quarter: &amp; then monthly you muſt waſh your trees with water, ſo high as a conny can reache wherein you muſt burſt the garbadg of a conny. Alſo euery weeke you muſt draw a peece of carraine at the foote of your payle in the bottome of your ditche round about your war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine, by which meanes your conies will neuer offer to touche your trees, nor come neere the payle to ſcrap the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues out. You muſt feede your connies with the ſhorteſt and ſweeteſt haye you can get: you may giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> graſſe, mallowes, cole wortes ſow thiſtles, the, tops of carrats, ſcar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rates, and any yeaths or weeds, they wil eate foure dayes in a weeke in ſommer, and two dayes in winter, but not aboue for feare of the rotte: yet let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue haie enough at al times, you may fatte them with graines mixed with oates, bran, or French wheate: you muſt giue your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nies euery day one oate ſheafe, which will alwayes keep them hearty, ſound, &amp; fayre skinned. I doe accompt your char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in keeping your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nies to be xx. markes a yeare, that is your warrainers board and wages, viii. li. and the conies meate v. li. vi. s. viii. d. the increaſe at an indifferent recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, wil be ſeuen litters a yeare: euery conie of the beſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3052:9"/>
kynde will bring vi. Rabbits at a litter, where one of that ſort bringeth fewer, two will bring moe, ſome will bring ix. litters in ayeare: &amp; that doe is not worth the keeping, that bringeth not vii. litters a yeare. The value of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe after the foreſayd rates, and at viii. d. the couple, (which <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> very ſkinnes with good huſbandrie of moſt of them wil be worth,) amounteth vnto the ſum of xliiii. li. xvi. s. a yeare. But for feare you ſhould fayle in your rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning, as the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did that ſuppoſed al the egges in her baſket were capons: I would haue you allow for ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualties, xi. li. ix. s. iiii. d. ſo reſteth aboue all charges of the warrainer, and their meate, xx. li. by yeare declaro, which I thinke being welvſed can yeeld no leſſe: although this kinde being bred in houſes do not eate ſweet, yet being bred after this manner, they are both the biggeſt, fatteſt, and ſweeteſt conies that are.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3052:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
